{"tossups": [{"question": "This island's Great Wall was similar in purpose to its Falca Lines. This island was home to the fortified Three Cities, and it was fed by the Floriana, Santa Margherita, and Cottonera Lines. This island's Fort Ricasoli was the site of the British army's Froberg Mutiny, and this island was defended by Forts Saint Michael and Saint Elmo after Gozo and Tripoli were conquered. The Knights Hospitaller [[HAH-spih-TAH-ler]] fought the Ottomans on this island in a 1565 Great Siege. For the point, name this Mediterranean island nation.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Malta</u></b> (accept <b><u>Melita</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Due to remarks he made about this event, Stephen Decatur [[dee-KAY-tuhr]] was shot and killed in a duel. This event resulted in the court-martial of James Barron, who was swiftly removed from command. In the aftermath of this event, James Monroe demanded the recall of Sir George Berkeley, as well as a ban on impressment against American ships. The Embargo Act of 1807 was passed in the aftermath of, for the point, what international incident, in which sailors from a British warship boarded an American frigate to search for deserters?", "answer": "<em><b><u>Chesapeake-Leopard</u></b></em> Affair (prompt on \"Chesapeake Affair\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Ciriaco [[see-ree-AH-koh]] de la Rosa claimed that he wanted to prevent an attack on this family but did not out of fear for his own life. While taking part in the 14th of June Movement, several members of this family began calling themselves \"The Butterflies.\" In 1960, three members of this family, along with their driver, Rafael de la Cruz, were assassinated while travelling to Puerto Plata. For the point, name this family which included Patria, Minerva, and Maria Teresa, three sisters who resisted the regime of Rafael Trujillo.", "answer": "<b><u>Mirabal</u></b> family (accept <b><u>Mirabal</u></b> sisters; accept Las Hermanas <b><u>Mirabal</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man put down the rebellion of Lucius Domitius Domitianus in Egypt and gave a gold stipend to Nobatia [[no-BAH-tyah]] and the Blemmyes [[BLEM-yehs]]. Shapur's son, Narseh, was defeated by this man, leading him to humiliate Galerius. Romanus of Caesaria, bishop Anthimus, and Peter Cubicularius [[kyoo-bih-kyoo-LAH-ree-us]] were executed by this man during his persecution of Christians. This leader, who signed the Edict of Maximum Prices, resolved the Crisis of the Third Century. For the point, name this Roman Emperor who established the tetrarchy.", "answer": "Gaius Aurelius Valerius <b><u>Diocletian</u></b> [[dai-oh-KLEE-shun]] (accept <b><u>Diocles</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This person justified his alcohol consumption by comparing wine to the instruction of a father. This philosopher memorized Aristotle's <em>Metaphysics</em> but claimed to not understand it until reading another philosopher's commentaries. This man tried to prove the soul's existence with his \"Floating Man\" thought experiment. This man and al-Farabi were criticized by al-Ghazali in <em>The Incoherence of the Philosophers</em>. For the point, name this Persian philosopher, the author of <em>The Canon of Medicine</em> and <em>The Book of Healing</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Avicenna</u></b> (or <b><u>Ibn Sina</u></b>; accept Abu <b><u>Ali Sina</u></b>; accept <b><u>Pur Sina</u></b>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This leader's government established the Transitional Justice Commission to investigate government atrocities over a nearly-fifty year period. To improve relations with countries such as Vietnam and Thailand, this leader launched the New Southbound Policy. This leader signed the Indigenous Languages Development Act, which added sixteen new national languages including Hakka. During one election, this leader's opponent, Hung Hsiu-chu [[SOO-CHOO]], was replaced due her pro-China rhetoric. For the point, name this first female president of Taiwan.", "answer": "<b><u>Tsai</u></b> Ing-wen (prompt on \"Ing-wen\")", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "One of these people named William Westwood died leading the Cooking Pot Uprising. Another of these people was shot by police at Goobang Creek three years after leading the Gardiner-Hall gang in robbing a gold escort at Escort Rock. David Maginnity [[mah-GIN-eh-tee]] and Thomas Smyth were shot by one of these people, \"Mad Dog\" Dan Morgan. Some of these people included Captain Moonlite and Captain Thunderbolt. After the Glenrowan affair, bulletproof armor was used by one of these people named Ned Kelly. For the point, name these escaped convicts in Australia.", "answer": "<b><u>Bushranger</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man's wife Marie-Anne Paulze translated works by Joseph Priestley and Henry Cavendish for her husband's use. Jacques-Louis David [[da-VEED]] painted this aristocrat and his wife surrounded by flasks and other lab equipment. This man, who pioneered stoichiometry by establishing the law of the conservation of mass, disproved the phlogiston theory and named both oxygen and hydrogen. For the point, name this French \u201cfather of modern chemistry,\u201d who was guillotined in the French Revolution.", "answer": "Antoine-Laurent de <b><u>Lavoisier</u></b> [[la-vwah-SEE-eh]]", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "While working for this organization, Scott Helvenston claimed that project manager Justin McQuown was \"very manipulative\" just days before being killed in an ambush. Andrew J. Moonen drunkenly killed a bodyguard protecting the vice president of Iran while employed by this organization. This company was awarded $21 million in exchange for protecting Paul Bremer, the head of the Coalition Provisional Authority. The Nisour Square Massacre was carried out by, for the point, what controversial private military company?", "answer": "<b><u>Blackwater</u></b> (accept <b><u>Xe Services</u></b>; accept <b><u>Academi</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An artifact from this city was sold by Willi Posselt to Cecil Rhodes, who was so inspired that he immediately funded an additional expedition to this city led by James Theodore Brent. Karl Mauch popularized a theory that structures at this location were meant to replicate the palace of the Queen of Sheba. This city's Eastern Enclosure was likely the location of eight soapstone sculptures of birds. Monarchs of the ancestral Shona people may have ruled from this city's Great Enclosure. For the point, name this ancient African city which lends its name to a southeast African nation.", "answer": "<b><u>Great Zimbabwe</u></b> (prompt on \"Zimbabwe\")", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "After this Kansas City musician moved to New York, he worked as a dishwasher at the Chicken Shack, where he caught the performances of piano legend Art Tatum. In songs like \u201cKo Ko\u201d and \u201cCherokee,\u201d this jazz instrumentalist developed the improvisational style that made him an icon of the Beat Generation. This creator of the jazz standard \"Ornithology,\" along with trumpeter Dizzy Gillespie, ushered in the era of BeBop. For the point, what virtuoso saxophonist was nicknamed \u201cBird?\u201d", "answer": "Charlie \"Bird\" <b><u>Parker</u></b> (prompt on \"Bird\" or \"Yardbird\")", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Jazz"}, {"question": "Scholars under this ruler created the \"Conduct of the Three Fundamental Principles in Human Relationships.\" This ruler gave maternity and paternity leave to the <em>nobi</em> slave class and ordered the Gihae [[GEE-HAY]] Eastern Expedition to remove Japanese pirates from Tsushima [[tsoo-SHE-mah]] Island. This ruler's Hall of Worthies created the Hunminjeongeum [hun-min-JONG-yum]], a treatise outlining the creation of a new writing system. Hangul was created by, for the point, what \"Great\" king of the Joseon dynasty?", "answer": "<b><u>Sejong</u></b> the Great (accept <b><u>Chungnyeong</u></b>; accept <b><u>Yi Do</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In the right foreground of this painting, Nicol\u00e1s Pertusato teases a mastiff with his foot, while Queen Mariana and King Philip IV can be seen reflected in a mirror on the back wall. On the left side of this painting, the artist depicted himself with the red cross of the Order of Santiago, of which he later became a member. The Infanta Margaret Theresa is the focus of several ladies-in-waiting and dwarfs in, for the point, what painting by Diego Vel\u00e1zquez?", "answer": "<em>Las</em> <em><b><u>Meninas</u></b></em> (accept <em>The</em> <em><b><u>Maids of Honor</u></b></em>; or <em>The</em> <em><b><u>Ladies-in-Waiting</u></b></em>, before mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "On this island, Ali Mughayat Syah [[moo-GAI-yaht SYAH]] was the first sultan of a particular region, while Alauddin Mansur Syah got the Ottoman Abdul Mecid I to decree protection over part of this island. This island was the site of the three-decade long Infidel War. In the Anglo-Dutch Treaty of 1824, British claims on Bencoolen and this island were traded for Indian land. Hasan Muhammad di Tiro proclaimed independence on this island, where the Free Aceh [[AH-chay]] Movement operated. For the point, name this Sunda Island, the westernmost major island of Indonesia.", "answer": "<b><u>Sumatra</u></b> (or <b><u>Sumatera</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The film <em>One Man\u2019s Hero</em> focuses on this unit which is remembered on the Wall of Honor in the Chamber of Deputies. Following William Worth's attack, many members of this group were captured and hanged at the Battle of Churubusco. This group was led by a U.S. army defector named John Riley. Fifty members of this group were executed, which remains the largest mass execution in U.S. history. For the point, name this military unit which fought for Mexico in the Mexican-American War under a flag with a yellow harp and sixteen shamrocks.", "answer": "Saint <b><u>Patrick</u></b>\u2019s Battalion (accept Batall\u00f3n de San <b><u>Patricio</u></b>s; accept Foreign Legion of <b><u>Patricio</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man led a meeting with nobles at Erfurt which ended when their combined weight caused them to collapse into the latrine below. This ruler also proposed the hereditary Erbreichsplan [[EHR-brike-shplahn]] and later married Constance, leading to his acquisition of Sicily. The death of this man led to the German Throne dispute between the Welfs and Hohenstaufens [[HOH-en-SHTOH-funs]]. The second son of Beatrix of Burgundy and Frederick Barbarossa, for the point, who was this late 12th century Holy Roman Emperor?", "answer": "<b><u>Henry VI</u></b> (or <b><u>Heinrich VI</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "For HBO\u2019s <em>Angels in America</em>, this person won a Golden Globe after playing a rabbi, an angel, a ghost, and a Mormon mother. In the first Oscar-winning role for this person in 1979, this actress played a mother engaged in a custody battle with her ex-husband, played by Dustin Hoffman. This actress won a Best Actress Oscar in 1982 for playing an Auschwitz survivor and another in 2012 for portraying Margaret Thatcher. For the point, what versatile actress starred in <em>Kramer vs. Kramer</em>, <em>Sophie\u2019s Choice</em>, and <em>The Iron Lady</em>?", "answer": "Meryl <b><u>Streep</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Eunus, a leader of one of these \u201cWars,\u201d claimed royal heritage and gave himself the regnal name Antiochus [[an-TAI-uh-kuss]]. Six thousand participants of one of these wars were crucified along the Appian Way. The third of these conflicts began when gladiators at a school in Capua revolted against a local Roman garrison, culminating in Crassus and Pompey\u2019s defeat of the slave army at the Silarius River. For the point, name these slave revolts of Ancient Rome, the third of which was led by Spartacus.", "answer": "<b><u>Servile</u></b> Wars (accept <b><u>Gladiator</u></b> War before mentioned; accept War of <b><u>Spartacus</u> </b>before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "During this event, Irish Defense Minister James Tully was injured by one of three grenades a soldier had hidden beneath a helmet. This event occurred during a parade to celebrate the eighth anniversary of a country's crossing of the Suez Canal. The target of this event lost a massive amount of popularity due to his signing of the Camp David Accords. Khalid Islambouli carried out, for the point, what attack, which resulted in the death of Gamal Nasser's successor, the third president of Egypt?", "answer": "<b><u>Assassination</u></b> of Muhammad Anwar el-<b><u>Sadat</u></b> (accept equivalents for \"assassination\" such as <b><u>killing</u></b>, <b><u>shooting</u></b>, or <b><u>murder</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During this conflict, Leandro Gomez was executed in the aftermath of the Siege of Paysand\u00fa [[pai-sahn-DOO]]. One side joined this conflict after Jos\u00e9 Ant\u00f4nio Saraiva issued an ultimatum in the face of stalled negotiations. To seize the Platine basin, Francisco Solano L\u00f3pez exploited this conflict, a move which led to Paraguay clashing with the Triple Alliance. For the point, name this war which ended after the Brazilian-backed Colorado party surrounded the Blanco party at Montevideo.", "answer": "<b><u>Uruguayan</u></b> War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This speech notes that its speaker's country has \"brought back a great mass of stores, rifles, and munitions of all kinds.\" This speech notes that in the \"dread balance-sheet\" there is \"great reason for intense vigilance and exertion but none whatever for panic or despair.\" On the same day as this speech, the Appeal of 18 June noted that \"France has lost a battle, but has not lost the war.\" For the point, name this speech, given one month after the \"Blood, toil, tears and sweat\" speech, in which Winston Churchill declared that the Battle of Britain was about to begin.", "answer": "\"This was their <b><u>finest hour</u></b>\" speech (be generous on words other than <b><u>finest</u></b> <b><u>hour</u></b>; prompt on descriptive answers about speeches by Winston Churchill before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s Chief Commandant and Blue Shirts leader Dai Li died in a plane crash orchestrated by his rival, spymaster Kang Sheng. During the Xian [[SHEE-AHN]] Incident, Zhang Xueliang [[ZHAHNG SHWAY-LYAHNG]] captured this leader and forced him to form the Second United Front with the Communists. This leader, whose Encirclement Campaign led to the CPC\u2019s \u201cLong March,\u201d later fled to Taiwan after losing a two-decade civil war. For the point, name this leader of Kuomintang [[KWOH-MIN-TAHNG]], the successor of Sun Yat-sen.", "answer": "<b><u>Chiang</u></b> Kai-shek (accept <b><u>Jiang</u></b> Jieshi; accept <b><u>Chiang</u></b> Chieh-shih; prompt on \"Kai-shek\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This figure's name first appeared in Geoffrey of Monmouth's pseudohistorical <em>History of the Kings of Britain</em>. This title character's play became controversial during the period of George III's madness, and its ending was changed during the Restoration for being too depressing. In that play, the Dukes of Albany and Cornwall are married to Goneril [[GAH-nuh-ril]] and Regan [[REE-gun]], respectively. For the point, what Shakespearean father foolishly divides his kingdom between his ungrateful daughters?", "answer": "<em>King</em> <em><b><u>Lear</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Drama"}, {"question": "A ruler of this state legendarily refused to convert to Islam due to his restrictions on alcohol, instead choosing to be baptized at Chersonesus [[kehr-soh-NAY-sus]]. Sviatopolk I [[SVYAH-tah-polk]] was deposed as the ruler of this state by his brother Yaroslav the Wise, who was aided by Varangian [[vah-RAHN-gee-an]] mercenaries. Nestor's <em>Primary Chronicle</em> claims that the first ruler of this federation was Oleg the Seer, who may have come from Novgorod. For the point, name this largely Slavic federation which was centered on a Ukrainian city.", "answer": "<b><u>Kievan Rus</u></b> (prompt on \"Kiev\"; prompt on \"Russia\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A leader of these people named Jean Guiton [[gwee-TOHN]] fought in the naval battle of Saint-Martin-de-R\u00e9 [[sahn-mahr-TANH-duh-REH]] against Charles, Duke of Guise [[GEEZ]]. These people, who were led by the Rohan brothers, lost power after La Rochelle was captured. The ill-fated George Villiers [[vee-YEH]], Duke of Buckingham, aided these people after initially supporting Cardinal Richelieu. Many of these people, including Admiral Coligny [[koh-lih-NYEE]], were slaughtered in the St. Bartholomew's Day Massacre. For the point, name these French Protestants.", "answer": "<b><u>Huguenot</u></b>s (prompt on \"Calvinists, \"Protestants,\" \"Christians\" or any of those words connected to \"France\" or \"French\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This party's rule over one city led the Armed Revolutionary Nuclei to launch the bombing at the Centrale [[chen-TRAH-leh]] railway station. This party fronted the Gullo Decrees and Garibaldi Brigades. Amadeo Bordiga [[BOR-dih-gah]] founded this party in 1921 alongside leaders of the <em>L'Ordine Nuovo</em> [[lor-DEE-neh NWOH-voh]]. This party cooperated in the Salerno Turn under a leader who was almost assassinated in 1948 by Antonio Pallante. Palmiro Togliatti and Antonio Gramsci [[GRAHM-she]] helped found this party. For the point, name this far-left party which increased its power after Mussolini's downfall.", "answer": "<b><u>Italian Communist</u></b> Party (accept <b><u>Communist</u></b> Party of <b><u>Italy</u></b>; accept Partito <b><u>Communista Italiano</u></b>; accept <b><u>PCI</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This leader, who styled himself \u201cBrother Number One,\u201d forced millions of city dwellers to move to the countryside in order to work on collective farms. This man became prime minister in 1975 after overthrowing Lon Nol's right-wing government. During a period in this man's country known as \u201cre-education,\u201d over a million people were killed and buried in the \u201cKilling Fields.\u201d For the point, what brutal Communist dictator led the Khmer Rouge regime in Cambodia?", "answer": "<b><u>Pol Pot</u></b> (accept Saloth <b><u>S\u00e2r</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In this country, 36 members of the Committee for Peasant Unity were killed by police while occupying a Spanish embassy. Elisabeth Burgos-Debray [[duh-BRAY]] added quotes from the Popol Vuh [[POH-pul VUH]] while translating a memoir written by an activist from this country. The conviction of Efra\u00edn R\u00edos Montt came after a genocide in this country was exposed by Rigoberta Mench\u00fa. For the point, name this Central American country whose 36-year-long civil war involved a systemic slaughter of its native Mayan population.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Guatemala</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In this city, Harold Macmillan gave his 1960 \"Winds of Change\" speech, and this city's colorful Bo Kaap neighborhood was established by Malay slaves who were freed by Britain in 1808. This is the most populous city in the ecologically-diverse fynbos [[FINE-bos]] biome, highlighted by a mountain, the first European of which to climb was Ant\u00f3nio de Saldanha, called Table Mountain. This city faced the 2018 \"Day Zero\" water crisis. For the point, name this South African city, which got its name from a geographic feature \u201cof Good Hope\u201d near the southern tip of Africa.", "answer": "<b><u>Cape Town</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This politician failed to convince Bruno Kreisky to keep a transit station open in the face of the Schoenau [[SHOOR-now]] ultimatum. The Gahal Party left a \"national unity\" coalition after this politician ended the War of Attrition. According to the Agranat Commission, this politician acted with \"common sense and speedily\" in response to an attack on the Bar Lev Line. This person resigned to match the \"will of the people\" in the aftermath of the Yom Kippur War. Yitzhak Rabin succeeded, for the point, which only female prime minister of Israel?", "answer": "Golda <b><u>Meir</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A king of an empire with this name led a ten-year campaign to conquer the oasis city of Tayma, in part to openly worship the moon goddess, Sin. A king of another empire with this name subjected Shadrach [[SHAD-rack]], Meshach [[ME-shack]], and Abednego [[ah-BED-neh-go]] to a fiery furnace according to the Book of Daniel. A millennium earlier, a king of a state with this name passed a namesake code which included the legal principle of \u201can eye for an eye.\u201d For the point, what name do the Mesopotamian empires of Hammurabi and Nebuchadnezzar II share?", "answer": "<b><u>Babylon</u></b>ian Empire (accept Neo-<b><u>Babylon</u></b>ian Empire; accept First <b><u>Babylon</u></b>ian Empire)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}], "bonuses": []}